setting up the printing space is just
one piece of the puzzle but can have a
big impact let's talk about how to set
up the press and the space around it to
maximize efficiency one of the most
important features of a screen printing
press is the printhead this is what
holds the screen many different press
configurations exist and fit different
types of shops
the one we're using today is a Riley
Hopkins 150 4x1
the 4 in 4x1 stands for the four print
heads and the one stands for the one
station
each print head has a screen clamp that
holds the screen the knobs hold the
screen tightly in place and allow you to
adjust the screen left to right and
front to back this allows you to align
the design to the perfect location on
the shirt the print head is attached to
the arm of the press it has the ability
to raise and lower the off contact of
the screen above the platen off contact
is the distance between the screen and
the plot to set up off contact clamp a
screen into the printhead typically off
contact is set between 1 16 and 1 8
inches place about four cleanup cards
between the platen and printhead to
create that space lower the print head
down into the registration gate on the
back of the printhead loosen all the
bolts so the screen can move freely
let the screen level out naturally as it
rests on the cleanup cards
once it's aligned tighten the bolts
again remove the cleanup cards and put
the screen down again you should be able
to see and feel an even space between
the screen and platen to keep the off
contact standard throughout a job it may
be a good idea to place a shim on the
front edge of the screen frame a washer
or quarter works great for this
you can loosen these bolts to adjust the
tilt of the printhead once the screen is
level tighten the bolts again manual
presses have registration gates to make
sure the print head sits in the same
place above the platen every time make
sure the print head fits snugly into the
registration gate once the screen has
proper off contact it's time to get the
platens prepped for a drop platens are
the surface you load shirts onto and
print on there are a couple of different
kinds of platens and they all need
proper care to stay in great condition
wood platens are the most affordable
option they are sturdy and durable but
are prone to warp over time especially
if they're not cared for properly
aluminum platens have a thinner profile
and offer more advantages than wood
platens for more info about the
differences between wood and aluminum
platens check out the blog in the class
description today we're using wood
platens make sure the platen is flat
properly placed on the arm if you're too
close to the registration gate the
screen won't be aligned since this is a
one station press we don't have to align
the spacing with other platens if you
have a press with more than one station
measure to make sure the platens are the
same distance away from the registration
gate
now let's draw some registration lines
on our platen registration lines help
you load a shirt and line up the film
perfectly every time many printers draw
registration lines directly on the
Platinum itself first draw a line down
the center of the platen this will be
your main reference point to make sure
the shirt is lined up with the center of
the design on the screen next draw three
horizontal lines one inch two inches and
three inches down from the top of the
platen these will help line the collar
of the shirt up in the right place
now that registration lines are drawn
let's talk about proper platen care
platen tape is necessary to keep your
platens in great condition for longer
without platen tape your platens will
get sticky and dirty with every job
they'll wear out faster and you'll have
to replace them sooner
here's how to apply plant tape first
make sure that the platen is clean of
dust and dirt roll the tape out a bit
and apply the sticky side to the platen
start with the edge of the platen
furthest away from you so you're rolling
toward yourself the key is to apply even
pressure so you don't get air bubbles
once the entire platen is covered let it
rest Loosely on the platen and cut it
with a sharp blade
use the razor blade to pop any small
bubbles or smooth them out if possible
make sure to trim the platen tape
cleanly instead of tucking it under the
platen
tucking the tape onto the platen creates
places where the shirt can catch or snag
when you're loading it
now we've taped our buttons so it's time
to take the screens taping screens is
super important you want the ink to only
pass through your design instead of the
edges of the screen that don't have
Emulsion it's important to use specific
screen printing tape other tapes can
break down when introduced to chemicals
or leave a sticky residue on the screen
that can cause problems later set the
screen down on a flat surface and pull
out a piece of tape a little bit longer
than the inside length of the screen
place the piece of tape on the mesh
first then secure it to the screen frame
make sure to tape any areas of the
screen that don't have Emulsion on them
a great hack is to lay down the tape in
either a clockwise direction or a
counterclockwise direction that way when
you're ready to take the tape off you
can pull it off all in one go now let's
finish setting up by getting our
printing space organized set up the
printing area where you can easily reach
anything you'll need during print having
a screen cart or utility cart nearby is
a big help Place everything you need for
the jaw on the cart this includes ink
adhesive a laser temp gun towels ink
spatulas squeegees and anything else
you'll use while printing place the
stack of shirts close by as well if
you're using a flash dryer you will want
to place the flash close enough to the
print station so you can easily reach
over and swivel it when it's time to
flash or cure a shirt if you're using a
conveyor dryer make sure the press and
conveyor are close together as well by
doing this everything needed is close by
you won't need to wander around the shop
searching for things and wasting time
our printing area is set up the print
head is ready and platens are prepped
next we'll register the design
welcome to how to screen print with a
kit the 150 Edition in this free course
I'll be walking you through every step
of the process from darkroom setup to
reclaim I'll be using the Riley Hopkins
150 kit it has everything you need to
start a screen printing hobby or side
Hustle
jump in today and get screen printing
tomorrow